Guide to the The Battle of 73 Easting, Gulf War Simulation Project Papers M1451
Department of Special Collections and University Archives
The Battle of 73 Easting, Gulf War: simulation project papers
1991-1993
Department of Special Collections and University Archives
Institute for Defence Studies and Analyses
M1451
5 Linear Feet (3 cartons, 1 map folder)
Papers concerning the simulation of a tank battle in the 1991 Gulf War.
Scope and Content of Collection
The simulation of this tank-on-tank engagement from the 1991 war against Iraq was run by the Institute for Defense Analyses and DARPA (the Defense Advanced Research Projects Agency). The product was a learning tool for current and future soldier training, as well as historical analysis. It became a model for further work in the same genre.
H.R. McMaster, who later became National Security Advisor, fought in the battle commanding the 2nd Armored Cavalry Regiment's Eagle Troop and contributed to the simulation project.
Biography / Administrative History
In February 26, 1991, two days into Operation Desert Storm, the allied VII Corps had moved through southern Iraq towards the Kuwait border. The 2nd Armored Cavalry Regiment had an initial encounter with ten Iraqi tanks which were destroyed near longitudinal line 60 (Easting 60); they moved on until the bulk of the battle occurred at 73 Easting. The visibility was almost zero because of dust storms and nightfall. It was this battle which the simulation project portrayed.
Acquisition Information
Gift of the Institute for Defense Analyses, 2004. Accession 2004-321.
Access
Collection is open for research; materials must be requested at least 36 hours in advance of intended use.
National security -- United States.; Military education -- United States.; war -- Computer simulation.; Persian Gulf War, 1991.; war -- Simulation methods.; War games.; Institute for Defence Studies and Analyses; United States. Defense Advanced Research Projects Agency; McMaster, H. R., 1962-
- Series 1. Research File, Series 1; 53 folder(s)
  - 1.1 Troop De-briefings, Subseries 1.1; 31 folder(s)
    - Platoon Briefing/Debriefing Notes (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - The Battle of 73 Easting: The Regiment's Perspective (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - Eagle Troop History Worksheet (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - Shoot History - Eagle Excel, 1992 Jan. 10 (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - Eagle Troop Interviews, 5 audio cassettes (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - Eagle Troop Tape 73 Easting, 2 CDs (Box 1, Folder 14)
    - Transcript of the Battle of 73 Easting - Eagle Troops (Box 1, Folder 15)
    - Eagle Troop Time Log 2 (from Iron Troop Transcripts), 1991 Feb. 26 (Box 1, Folder 16)
    - 73E Mcmaster - Eagle Troop (Box 1, Folder 17)
    - Selected Personnel Statistics Eagle Troop, Second Squadron, Second Armored Cavalry Regiment, VII Corps (Box 1, Folder 18)
    - Iron Troop Interview (Box 1, Folder 19)
    - I Troop Radio 73 Easting, 1 audio cassette (Box 1, Folder 20)
    - Iron Troop History Worksheet (Box 1, Folder 21)
    - Iron Troop Riring Event Log, 1991 Feb. 26 (Box 1, Folder 22)
    - Problems w/ Iron-Eagle Interaction, 1991 Aug. 14 (Box 1, Folder 23)
    - Ghost Interview Tape Transcript (Box 1, Folder 24)
    - Ghost Troop Firing Event Log - 1, 1991 Feb. 26 (Box 1, Folder 25)
    - Ghost Troop History Worksheet (Box 1, Folder 26)
    - Events & Experiences of the 82nd Engineer Batallion (Box 1, Folder 27)
    - Iraqi Fire Date Static & Dynamic, 1991 Oct. 31 (Box 1, Folder 28)
    - Events of 2/26/91 from 2dA, 1991 Aug. 23 (Box 1, Folder 29)
    - 73E Vignettes (Box 1, Folder 30)
    - Iraqi Moving Vehicles 11/8/91 Red Team Positions 11/6/91, 1991 Nov. (Box 1, Folder 31)
    - Documentation in Arabic (Box 1, Folder 32)
    - Troop Movements & Timelines (Box 2, Folder 1)
    - 73 Easting Audio Files, 1 CD (Box 2, Folder 9)
    - Shoot History Iron, 1992 Jan. 17 (Box 2, Folder 13)
    - Movement - Iron, 1992 Jan. 17 (Box 2, Folder 14)
    - Shoot History - Iron (Box 2, Folder 15)
    - Movement - Ghost (Box 2, Folder 17)
    - 3rd Armored Division Operation Desert Storm (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - 1.2 Data, Subseries 1.2; 22 folder(s)
    - 73 Easting Re-Creation Databook Draft (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - 73 Easting Re-Creation Databook Draft (Copy) (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - SIMNET 101 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - DARPA Memos, Conference Letters, Troop Background (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - 73 Easting Positioning/Target Questions, 1991 Sept. 26 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Snapshot Grids (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - (Simulation Data) Dumplogs, 1991 Nov. 27 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Required Additional Terrain Features: Berms & Dug on Positions in Area of Interest (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - Thorpe (Box 1, Folder 33)
    - NATO IRIS (Box 2, Folder 2)
    - Position Updates - 73E ODIN Printouts, 1991 Sept. 26 (Box 2, Folder 3)
    - Historical Worksheet (Box 2, Folder 4)
    - Verification & Validation of Battle of 73 Easting (Box 2, Folder 5)
    - Printouts of Shooters, Targets, Results, etc. (Box 2, Folder 6)
    - db 733coh.oor, 1 1/4" data cartridge (Box 2, Folder 7)
    - 73 Easting Battle Recreation Data, 3 3.5" diskettes (Box 2, Folder 8)
    - M Tapes, 4 audio cassette tapes (Box 2, Folder 10)
    - M Tapes mini, 2 audio mini cassette tapes (Box 2, Folder 11)
    - Commander's Guide: Using SIMNET to see the Battlefield (Box 2, Folder 12)
    - ODIN Printouts, Time Points, Database Work (Box 2, Folder 16)
    - Historical Worksheets - Vehicle by Vehicle (Box 2, Folder 18)
    - Maps (paper copies) (Box 2, Folder 19)
- Series 2. Finished Simulation, Series 2; 3 folder(s)
  - 2.1 73 Easting Functional Description & Guidance Document, First Draft (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - 2.2 Instructions to Setup 73 Easting Maps (Box 2, Folder 22)
  - 2.3 New 73 Easting Instructions (Box 2, Folder 23)
- Series 3. Publicity, Series 3; 60 folder(s)
  - 3.1 Presentations, Series 3.1; 14 folder(s)
    - 73E demo, 1 100mb zip disk (Box 2, Folder 24)
    - War Breaker - ARPA Logo, 1993 Nov. 7; 1 hi8 digital video cassette (Box 2, Folder 25)
    - 73 Easting Methodology (Box 2, Folder 26)
    - 73E Final (Box 2, Folder 27)
    - 73 Easting A Simulation to Capture Actual Gulf War Battles (Box 2, Folder 28)
    - Refighting the Battle of 73 Easting (Box 2, Folder 29)
    - Production Slides: Maps, Planning (Box 3, Folder 5)
    - 2ACR OPN Desert Storm (Box 3, Folder 6)
    - The Battle of 73 Easting 26 Feb 1991 A Historical Introduction to Simulation, 1991 Feb. 26 (Box 3, Folder 14)
    - 73E Review (Box 3, Folder 15)
    - 73 Easting Re-Creation Validation & Verifications (Box 3, Folder 16)
    - LCDR Dennis McBride: Project ODIN (Box 3, Folder 17)
    - 73 Easting Videotape Script (Box 3, Folder 22)
    - Defense Science Board (Box 3, Folder 41)
  - 3.2 Conferences, Series 3.2; 42 folder(s)
    - Introduction & Background Working Conference on 73 Easting Construction of a Battle in Interactive Simulation (Box 2, Folder 30)
    - 73 Easting Conference (Box 2, Folder 31)
    - Conf 1991 Apr. 11, 1991 May 11, 1991 Apr. - 1991 May; 2 reels magnetic tape (Box 2, Folder 32)
    - Jim Wargo's 73 Easting Stuff (Box 2, Folder 33)
    - Paul Kozemchak on R&D Budgets (Box 2, Folder 34)
    - Keynote Address (Box 2, Folder 35)
    - Slideshow Battle of 73 Easting Development (Box 2, Folder 36)
    - Conference Report (Box 2, Folder 37)
    - Rough Cut, 1992 Apr. 8; 1 beta cassette (Box 2, Folder 38)
    - 73E (Box 3, Folder 1)
    - 73E / Janus (Box 3, Folder 2)
    - Colonel Gary Bloedorn (Box 3, Folder 3)
    - Col Gary Bloedorn 73E Presentation Corrected, 1 3.5" diskette (Box 3, Folder 4)
    - General Paul Gorman (Box 3, Folder 7)
    - Gen Gorman 73E Corrected, 13.5" diskette (Box 3, Folder 8)
    - General Welch (Box 3, Folder 9)
    - 73E Gen Welch Corrected & New Questions, 1 3.5" diskette (Box 3, Folder 10)
    - General Max Thurman (Box 3, Folder 11)
    - Dr. Randy Steeb (Box 3, Folder 12)
    - Jesse Orlansky: Drawing Inferences from Battlefield Statistics (Box 3, Folder 13)
    - Major General Paul Funk (Box 3, Folder 18)
    - 73E MajGen Paul Funk Not Corrected (Box 3, Folder 19)
    - Col Krausse's 73 Easting A-F (maps) PVD (Box 3, Folder 20)
    - Galloway (Box 3, Folder 21)
    - Jim Metzger Army ODCSOPS (Box 3, Folder 23)
    - Dr. Metzger 73E Corrected, 1 3.5" diskette (Box 3, Folder 24)
    - Major General Matthew Caulfield USMC (Box 3, Folder 25)
    - MG Cualfield 73E Not Corrected, 1 3.5" diskette (Box 3, Folder 26)
    - Richard Allen RADM (Box 3, Folder 27)
    - Richard Bronowitz, Team Mike CNA (Box 3, Folder 28)
    - Dr. Bronowitz 73E old draft (Box 3, Folder 29)
    - Dr. Johnson ARI (Box 3, Folder 30)
    - Kozemchak (Box 3, Folder 31)
    - Dr. Andy Ceranowicz: Constructing the Simulation (Box 3, Folder 32)
    - Dr. Ceranowicz 73E Presentation Corrected, 1 3.5" diskette (Box 3, Folder 33)
    - Colonel Doc Coughtery, USAF (Box 3, Folder 34)
    - Col Doughtery 73E Corrected, 1 3.5" diskette (Box 3, Folder 35)
    - George E. Lukes: Methodology: Terrain Database Development (Box 3, Folder 36)
    - Colonel Jack thorpe, USAF: 73 Easting Reconstruction in Interactive Simulation (Box 3, Folder 37)
    - Maj Lutte 73E Corercted, 1 3.5" diskette (Box 3, Folder 38)
    - Dr. Johnson 73E, 1 3.5" diskette, 1 5" disk (Box 3, Folder 39)
    - Misc Media, 2 3.5" diskette, 1 audio cassette (Box 3, Folder 40)
  - 3.3 Publicity, Series 3.3; 3 folders and 1 map folder
    - "Emulating the Battlefield," IEEE Spectrum, September 1991 (Box 3, Folder 42)
    - "Battle of 73 Easting: A Historical Simulation," National Defense, November 1991 (Box 3, Folder 43)
    - Newspaper Clippings (Box 3, Folder 44)
    - 4 Blowups - Exhibit (Othertype 4)